Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> Good evening, good day everybody and
welcome back to the Ask Today we are
going to discuss history, Indian history
and world history. I welcome you all
back to the show. Uh let us see before
we start who all is there on the live
stream on the live chat. I can see real
Vladimir Putin geopolitical dub from
Indor Sumuk Bupalam
Shya Rod
Udb Sharma Victor Victor Nitro Adwit
Ashwini good evening um Diva Di Viva
okaydurya Swami is here Ritik Bardage
Minwise Laksha Sharma online good to see
you sir wise idiot [laughter]
pri
Rakshit Mishra Kunicha Sandy PM5HU
Namaskar Victor Night Road once again
Swami is here from Jaipur Lego online
once again geopolitical once again
Nirvana Shanks Kuricha Kuricha Mac 4
random skull is here from Karnavati nice
to see you Balki today namaste Rajat
Duhan Salpumra
Ashish Chabra
Raj Raja Akash Kumar good evening Nutan
Roshan namast Kam you sir 01 Ram Ram
Abhishek 107 Anish 1784 hello Sandy once
again Vikash PJ Omnak Namaskar Pranka
Javalia good evening ma'am um Vikash PJ
once again rit 08 hello good to have you
an ANI motion clips JO uh yos sir Mac4
Jagdish Mali hello uh Alishia Bahara
hello Gajapati Dave
Vikas PJ once again. Somi Game of
Thrones Breaking Bad. I'm not sure what
that is. Uh yeah, I know. I've seen some
of that. Wise idiot once again watching
live after a long time. Well, good to
have you. Welcome back. Brave robot
Gorov D. Uh Yoser is here from Kerala.
Good to have you from Kerala. Hello to
Kerala. Everybody there. Uh critical
thinker 24.
Is it Saturday? No, it's a Friday. I'm
traveling on Sunday. That's why I'm
doing it on Friday and Saturday this
week. this weekend. Rishuk, Dashupta,
Panduranga, Rola, Real Vanir, Putin,
Prardana, Namaste, Super Rex, Trap
Nation, Amish Mishra, hello. Um, Somi
once again, Annie is here. Hello, Bala.
Subramanyam, good evening.
Hari Ban Banana Hegard is here from
Danbad. Well, good to have you. Uh, Game
of Thrones or Breaking Bad, which would
I choose? Season 1 to four, Game of
Thrones was outstanding. breaking but
overall was outstanding. Both are
equally good. That's what I would say.
Okay. Uh Yosir Adatwini Ara
6258 Gan Madala Critical Thinking and
everybody else. Okay, let's get going
with some questions. Okay, I will take
as many questions as possible today as
always uh in the next couple of hours.
Let's see how many I can take. We're
going to discuss various aspects of
history, Indian history, world history.
And it is that time of the year when we
should perhaps begin with this question.
Ainta Anand says, "What were the reasons
the why the Vatican ordered the burning
of documents related to the Spanish
Inquisitions in India? And what kind of
atrocities did these individuals commit
that these documents needed to be
burned? First of all,
there wasn't a Spanish Inquisition in
India. There was an inquis inquisition
that's called the Goa Inquisition. It
was So, how did the Goa Inquisition
begin? So the Portuguese
were in the were at the time let's say
in the 16th century in occupation of
Goa. They had captured parts of Goa,
western India, west coast of India and
they were occupying Goa and they wanted
to convert everybody to Christianity.
They did not like India's indigenous
culture and religions. So there was this
fantastic gentleman whose name was
Francis Xavier.
You may have seen various schools in
India
named St. Xavier school, St. Xavier's
College and so on. It's a very popular
name in in India for schools and
colleges. St. Xavier. So this individual
Francis Xavier is who these St. Xavier
schools and colleges are named after.
Okay. So this person Francis Xavier was
a missionary. He was a Jesuit missionary
and he was in Goa in the 16th century.
Okay. Um let's say middle of the 16th
century 1500s 1550s 1560 around that
time. Okay. And this guy maybe maybe
1540s. He died in 1550 something. Okay.
Francis Xavier. So before that when he
was in Goa he wrote to the king of
Portugal asking for an inquisition in
Goa because the people of Goa though
some of them had been forcibly converted
to Christianity they were secretly
practicing Hinduism and they were
secretly keeping idols evil idols of
Indian deities in their houses and
secretly praying to them that sort of
thing. So something had to be done about
these things. Something had to be done
about these people, these evil Indians
who would not convert properly to
Christianity in Goa. So Francis Xavier
wrote to the king of Portugal and he
asked for a proper inquisition in India
in Goa. So the Goa Inquisition begins
somewhere around 1560. Okay.
So the Goa Inquisition was this brutal
oppression of the people of of of
occupied Goa. Um anyone who was accused
of being a heretic or being a
cryptohindu or being disrespectful to
Christianity etc. they would be they
would be brought to the the court the
the inquisition court tribunal and
sometimes they would be in prison for
years before they would actually the the
hearing would happen and they would be
tortured in the hearing. So first of all
they would not be told who had accused
them of whatever. Secondly
uh they would be tortured in a variety
of horrific ways. You know the Europeans
the the the the Catholics came up with
all kinds of most horrific torture
methods. Uh I shall not go into the
specifics and the details. You can look
it up online. They had these instruments
that would tear the breasts of women and
they would u they would u they had
something called strap. I'm just giving
you two or three examples. Strap or
something. They would hang a person uh
you know from their wrists but behind
the body and then they would drop the
person repeatedly so that the shoulders
would get dislocated and the person
would be in agonizing pain forever
essentially. Uh there was something
called um what was it called? Yeah,
there were I I forget the names. Okay,
there are all kinds of horrific names of
these various torture methods and
instruments. Um there was the gat which
was a method of execution. uh there was
something called the oto dafay that was
public burning of people alive some
people would have had have their hands
cut off there was this there is this
famous uh pillar in Goa the hut katros
tamb it's called I believe where I don't
know how many thousands of people had
their hands cut off so all kinds of
horrific brutal um methods of torture
and oppression and murder okay a murder
sanctioned by the church uh the
objective was to ensure that Hindus did
not recon convert or did not practice
Hinduism in in in private. The the the
objective was to intimidate and
brutalize the people so badly that they
would become devout Christians. That
sort of thing. Okay. And they held God
knows how many trials of people and all
all of that was recorded. All of this
was recorded. Okay. So this begins in
the mid6th century 1560 or something
onwards
and then after a century or two by the
by the early 1800s after a century and a
half of horrific oppression uh
destruction of temples they they they
re-engineered the Indian society you
know historically societ villages would
have their own village institutions like
panchiads or whatever. So the Portuguese
imposed new rules that you know uh no
decision could be made unless unless uh
all the Christians who had converted to
Christianity in the village were present
in the assembly or meeting or whatever
and the head had to be Christian and all
kinds of such rules were made such that
people had no choice but to eventually
get you know have to be forced to
convert to Christianity. temples were
destroyed. Um, Hindu priests were not
allowed to officiate in weddings. Um,
and and all kinds of atrocious rules and
of course the torture and the executions
of people burning people alive of that.
So this went on for a century and a half
roughly and all the trials all the
proceedings were recorded in great
detail by the Portuguese. Now on the in
the early 1800s you have the rise of the
Marata Empire. by the time it becomes
the dominant force right the Marata
Empire
um in the well in the in the 18th
century in the 1700s 1750s the Marata
Empire reaches the peak of its power and
eventually the Maratas go after you know
that there is conflict between the
Maratas and the Portuguese. So in the
early 19th century the Portuguese
viceroy
in Goa he decided that the that the
records the documents the archive of the
inquisition all the proceedings all the
all the people who were tortured all the
people who were accused all the people
who were executed in various forms
various ways etc. this archive, this
documentation was politically dangerous.
That's what the Portuguese viceroy
decided. So he ordered the destruction
of the overwhelming majority of the uh
records of the inquisition. So it was
not ordered by the Vatican, it was
ordered by the Portuguese viceroy in
Goa. This happened in the early 19th
century, okay? In the early 1800s.
So, so what they did was they took some
selected records a few I don't know what
the quantity of the records was and
those records the whatever that they
felt were the most important or whatever
was worth preserving they sent these
records to the Portuguese court in
Brazil in Rio de Janeiro. Okay. And
these apparently are still there in the
in the national library in Rio de
Janeiro Brazil.
uh and the rest of the documentation,
the rest of the archives, the rest of
the documents were all burned,
destroyed. We have no idea how much
documentation was burned uh from the
documents that do exist. It looks like
there were like some 15 to 20,000 trials
were were performed based on whatever
has survived and it says maybe 200
people were executed. That's what it
says roughly. Okay. [laughter] But the
overwhelming majority of the of the
records were destroyed, burned. So that
is what happened. It wasn't the Spanish
Inquisition. It was the Goa Inquisition
conducted by the Portuguese uh it wasn't
the Vatican that ordered the burning
burning or destruction of documents. It
was the viceroy, the Portuguese viceroy
of Goa in the early 19th century who
decided this has to be done because it
was too politically etc dangerous. It
would show Portugal in a bad light. It
would show Christianity in a bad light.
All the nasty stuff, horrific atrocities
they had done, all the records probably
were meticulously listed and documented.
All of it was destroyed.
So these were human rights abuses.
This was possibly genocide at a certain
scale. Now we don't know, right? We can
only
rely on perhaps the oral records of of
people who passed passed down passed
down the stories. Most of them
eventually became so fervently Catholic
that they denied anything. I mean
talking about the goans
those who converted are they eventually
became so fervently Catholic that they
denied anything had had been done to
their ancestors and so on. Over time
this that's that gets into your blood I
suppose. Uh so most
of the evidence has been destroyed by
the Portuguese by the by the by the
church by the by the well the records
were in the
in the custody of the church people I
suppose of the Portuguese. So they
destroyed it all to hide what they had
done to Indians. So that today if you
try to look back upon the the the that
part of the history we don't have any
actual records of what the Portuguese
did apart from the little bit that is in
the national library in Rio de Janeiro
Brazil. So they destroyed the evidence.
It's like the Nazis destroying evidence
of the Holocaust all the records of the
Holocaust that that sort of thing the
Portuguese did in India. So the
atrocities they committed, we will never
know. I suppose the the the scale of the
brutality, the scale of the atrocities,
we'll never know.
Um so this was done to cover up their
tracks. It was done to cover up their
atrocities, their human rights abuses,
their their genocide, their you know
what they did. So it must have been
horrific. It must have been so horrific
that they decided it was it should not
ever be made public and that's why they
burned it all. All right. So that was
the deal about the Goa Inquisition
brought into India by Francis Xavier.
This Jesuit missionary.
Okay.
Math and CL um yeah says what are the
origins of the Bath party? The ba party
in the Arab world. Two very
consequential leaders Saddam Hussein and
Hafis al-Haz Assad were ba'ists.
Were they aligned in their goals and
worldviews? The bath party. So what is
the bath party? It is the party that
Saddam Hussein belonged to. It is the
party that Haf al-Assad belonged to and
as a consequence Bashar al-Assad, his
son also belonged well you could say to
the Bath party. So, how come? So, first
of all, we're talking about Iraq and
Syria. Where is Iraq? Where is Syria?
Let's find out. Let's uh let's go to the
map and figure out the which part of the
world are we talking about? We're
talking about West Asia obviously.
So, let's let's focus on that that part
of the world. So, if you are in India,
go westwards, cross the temporary
nation, cross Gandhar, we have Persia,
you cross Persia, go further west, we
come to Iraq and Syria. So, we're
talking about these two nations. The
capital of Iraq is Baghdad and the
capital of Syria is Damashk or Damascus.
Okay, these two nations we're talking
about. So there was this political party
that encompassed both these nations
actually. How did that happen? Right.
And uh how did the leaders of two
nations belong to the same political
party? It's a very good question, isn't
it? The Bath party. So what's the story?
What's the history of the Bath party?
The origins of the Bath party go back to
the 1940s. We're talking about a time a
time when the world was at war, the
Second World War. Okay, the 1940s we're
talking about. Um, and there were two
Syrian intellectuals. One was a
Christian. There are Christians
apparently in Syria. So, one was a
Christian and one was a Muslim. I you
can look up their names. One was Michel
something. The other was Saladin
something Salah something. two
intellectuals, one Muslim, one
Christian. They founded something called
the Arab Renaissance Movement in Syria
in Damascus. And the objective, the goal
was to promote Arab nationalism. But
what kind of Arab nationalism? Secular
Arab nationalism. Okay, it starts with
secularism. And it's not surprising
given the way it it eventually uh
evolves because Saddam Hussein, Iraq was
a secular nation by the way. It was not
an Islamic nation officially. it was a
secular nation. So the origins are in
Damascus in the 1940s. Uh it is these
two Syrian intellectuals who who who
start this movement, the Arab
Renaissance movement. The [snorts]
objective is to promote secular Arab
nationalism. Okay. And this movement was
formally established in 1947. I think
that's a date all Indians can remember.
It was established as the resurrection
party. Now how do you say resurrection
in Arabic? You say bath. So it became
the bath party or the resurre
resurrection party and they adopted a
constitution based on various pillars
like unity and freedom and socialism.
Okay, socialism. Uh so it was about um
Arab nationalism. It was about unity,
freedom, national socialism. It was
about decolonizing the region because it
was under you know it had been under
European control for a very long time.
Right? Uh so that's what happened and in
the 1950s the bath party it merged with
the Syrian Socialist Party and it was
eventually renamed as the Arab Socialist
Bath party. Okay, so that's in the 1950s
but it's still just a movement. It's not
in power. Now in 1963
in Syria uh military officers of the
Syrian military of the Syrian army who
were aligned with the Bath party who
belonged to the Bath party they they
conducted a coupa in Syria and they
seized power in Syria. So the bath party
in 1963 comes to power in Syria and
it's in the 1960s that uh Hafas al-Assad
becomes a prominent leader a prominent
politician and uh Haf as al-Assad
sometime in the 1960s he engineers a
split of the party of the movement into
two camps the Syrian camp and the Iraqi
camp or the Syrian branch and the Iraqi
branch and their ideologies and agendas
start diverging in the 1960s. Then in
the Iraqi branch of the Bath party it
conducted
a coup da in Iraq in Baghdad and they
took control of the government in
Baghdad and it was a person called
al-Bakr who became the president of
Iraq. He was the first baist president
of Iraq. So eventually Hafes al-Assad
becomes the most prominent guy in Syria
to the east uh to the west of Iraq.
Right? And uh in the 1970s he becomes uh
the most powerful person in the bath
party in Syria. He assumes total control
and total power. Hafes al-Assad and the
western historians will tell you that he
established a security state a
totalitarian security state and you know
it was rooted in a cult of personality.
It was rooted in personal loyalty to the
man Hafes al-Assad and
the core officers who were loyal to
Hafes al-Assad were the Alawites the
Alawi they belong to the minority Alawi
uh sect of the Syrian population. Okay.
So that's uh in the 1970s. Then there is
transformation in Iraq as well. And in
1979,
Saddam Hussein emerges and becomes the
president of Iraq. He forces out this
the person who had who had become the
first president, Mr. Al-Bakr. He forces
him out and he becomes the president of
Iraq. And then in a very famous
televised
uh
conference or something a meeting in a
very large hall he publicly purged all
his rivals in the bath party to
completely and totally consolidated
power within his person. So there there
are there's a recording there are
multiple recordings recordings of this
available on YouTube. Okay. It's a black
and white recording in which Saddam
Hussein is sitting
um on the stage and he has he's got
these papers with him. He's smoking a
cigar and he's reading out names one by
one. He says that if I read your name
out and there's a huge audience in front
of him. He says that if I read your name
out, stand up, recite the party slogan
and and go outside of the of the hall
where you will be taken care of, let's
say.
And uh that becomes I mean killing
killing name after name comes up the
person has to stand up some people
protest they are escorted out they're
pulled out and one can imagine what
happened to those people whose names
were spoken by Saddam Hussein you know
called out by Saddam Hussein so Saddam
Hussein becomes the all powerful
leader of Iraq right u so that is what
happened then in the 70s late '7s there
Of course, there were some attempts to
unify the Syrian and Iraqi states, you
know, but uh you see, when you have two
strong [snorts] leaders, there's going
to be ego clashes. There's going to be
rivalry. So, you have Saddam Hussein in
Iraq, you have Hafes al-Assad in Syria,
[snorts] they would not get along,
right? Uh and then the two nations
become rivals. They become rivals to
such an extent that when there was the a
war between Iraq and Iran which is from
1980 to 1988
the Iran Iraq war
at that time Syria sided with Iran not
with Iraq despite both parties being
ruled by both nations being ruled by the
bath party. Right? So Syria took the
side of Iran when Iran was at war with
Iraq despite Syria being ruled by the
Bath party by the Syrian Baist party and
Iraq being ruled by the Iraqi party bath
party. So clearly the two nations were
not aligned. The two leaders were not
aligned. They were on opposite ends of
the uh well they were essentially rivals
and that caused rivalry between the two
nations themselves. Um [clears throat]
and that essentially is the story of the
bath party and eventually now Hafes
al-Assad gave you know he he once he
passed away u the power was taken by his
son you know the mantle or the beton or
the crown let's say passed on to his son
Bashar al-Assad who was ousted recently
this year by
by Alfar who is a former terrorist
formerly wanted terrorist ISIS
terrorists, that sort of thing. Yeah.
So, regime change operation has happened
successfully. And the Bath party is no
longer in power in Syria. And when it
comes to Iraq, it was uh the Bath party
was ousted in what 2003 was it when the
Americans invaded Iraq for the second
time and obliterated the nation. So that
was the story of the Bath party. Um the
Bath party's origins are in Syria. A
Muslim and
a Christian
came together to to start this movement
that eventually became the Bath party.
Two very consequential leaders Saddam
Hussein and Hafes al-Assad were both
bist baists but they were not aligned in
any way in their goals and they were
actually rivals and the Syrian bath
party lasted longer than the Iraqi Bath
party and both were ended by a foreign
power the same foreign power the United
States. That's the story of the Bath
party.
Amisha says, "How was the Kingdom of
Spain able to colonize such vast swath
of Central and South America without
other nations competing?" Well, you see,
in business, there is something called
first mover's advantage.
If you if you come up with a technology
for the first time, if you're the first
to come up with a technology, then
you're going to have an advantage and
you're going to move into the market
first, right? And that's what happens.
So
Spain, what happens is let's look at the
chronology
in 1492. Christopher Columbus uh he is
given this big charter or whatever you
want to call it by the king and queen of
Spain Isabella and Ferinand. They give
him money, they give him ships, etc. And
the objective is Christopher Columbus
promises them, I'm going to go and
discover India and I'm going to colonize
India and I'm going to bring back all
the wealth and make you super fabulously
rich. there was the deal. So they give
him what he wants and he goes and
crosses the Atlantic. He goes westwards
instead of going eastwards because if
you go eastwards you have to cross the
Turkish occupied territories and that
was a problem. They could not do that.
So so they knew how to reach India from
the east. But that the route was cut off
by the Ottoman Turks. So they had the
Christopher Columbus at the time knew
that the uh the earth is round. It's
spherical. It was newly discovered by
the Europeans at the time. a few
thousand years too late but whatever. So
Christopher Columbus goes westwards and
he stumbles into the Caribbean region
and he imagines that he has discovered
India. So in in 1492 Christopher
Columbus discovers let's say America. He
very rapidly colonizes Hispanola, Cuba
and the the surrounding region. Um
then the Portuguese also are they are
very capable. Okay they they at the time
had a very capable navy etc. So they
also said why should we get left out but
then they had a good relationship or or
a working relationship with the kingdom
of Castillia which is Spain. So the
Spanish and the and the Portuguese they
decided to carve up the world divide the
world among each other in such a way
that they do not they would not have to
compete and fight. That was the treaty
of theas 1494. Yeah you can look it up.
And they they divided the world along a
north north south meridian that sort of
thing. the the western part the western
part of this would be taken over by the
the the the Spanish and the eastern part
would be taken over by the by the
Portuguese. They would be free to
colonize all non-Christian nations in
the eastern half and the Spanish would
be free to colonize all non-Christian
nations or or or cultures in the uh
western half. So it was all about
colonization. It was all about
occupation, plunder, slavery and and uh
conversion to Christianity. Okay. So and
at this time it's only Spain and
Portugal that are the big guys. Okay.
They had the techn technological knowhow
the cap capabilities to do these things.
They had the navy. They had the navies
that could do this. They were their
navies were better than any other
European navies and they had the money
that was coming in from the crowd.
And that's how the Spaniards went ahead
and colonized first u um the Aztec
Triple Alliance and then the Inca
Empire. Brutal brutal stuff as we know
as we've discussed many times in the
past. Um
and the and the Portuguese went
eastwards. They colonized various parts
of Africa. They came to India. They
tried doing their thing over here in
India and they brutalized Goa and that
sort of thing. Right? So so Spain had
the first war advantage in Central and
South America.
Now by the 1550s other nations were like
why should we get left behind? So the so
the French start, you know, attempting
to to put down a tow hold somewhere in
the Americas and they they try and fail
several times. Eventually they end up in
no in the northern half of North
America, the Quebec, Canada region,
right? Um and that's a whole different
story. That's much later.
And the English also uh the English at
the time did not have a powerful navy.
Uh
so they also were interested in the
Americas. They also were interested in
colonizing the whole world. Right?
And at the in the 1500s
these efforts of England were subsidized
by the crown.
Who was the crown? It was Elizabeth,
Queen Elizabeth.
So she what she did was she she financed
various piracy operations. These pirates
were called privateeers
and they would engage in piracy in
murder in slavery all financed by
the British crown. But it's only in the
six early 1600s
that the British came up with a
different way of doing things. the
various British private citizens,
wealthy private citizens, merchants,
they formed joint stock companies and
that
was the means by which they finance the
East India Company and so and various
colonization efforts even in the
Americas.
Uh so that's how everything changes and
we're talking about the 1600s here
that's when we have uh Jamestown and all
Plymouth and all that. So for a century
or so the Spaniards and the Portuguese
were able to divide the world into two
halves and uh because of first war
advantage they were able to do a lot and
the Spaniards become very became very
wealthy as a consequence because of the
conquest of the Aztec triple alliance
empire and the Inca Empire which were
very populist very wealthy they were
able to uh you know have as many slaves
as they wanted. tremendous quantities of
gold flowed into Spain which was able to
finance further Spanish activities and
and wars and military operations and
whatnot. But eventually the British
model proved to be superior.
So that's why the Spaniards because of
first mover advantage were able to
colonize vast regions of Spain of
Central and South America.
Amisha says Britain, Spain, and Portugal
had three of the biggest empires back in
the day. However, why do Spain and
Portugal have very little power or
influence on the world stage today
unlike Britain in present day politics?
Well, even Britain has zero advantage
today. Zero influence, zero power. But
the continuation of the British Empire,
which is the American Empire, is the all
powerful entity in the world today. So,
you could say that the British Empire
still is the predominant hegemonic
entity in the world in the shape and
form of the American Empire. It has
morphed into something different, but
it's a continuation of the same entity.
Okay.
So yeah, you could say that the Anglo
Empire continues and and still
predominates. It is the hegemonic empire
in the world today. But Spain and
Portugal, well, they they don't matter
anymore. They are completely
marginalized. They they simply don't
matter geopolitically today. Why is that
so? Well, ask yourself this question. In
the 18th century, the Marata Empire was
all powerful in India in the Indian
subcontinent.
What happened to it? It doesn't even
exist anymore. Similarly, the Spanish
Empire doesn't exist anymore. The
Portuguese empire doesn't ex exist
anymore. They still the Spaniards still
have their their royal family like the
crown so on. It's just a nominal thing.
It's a tradition that they are holding
on to. In India, we have we have
destroyed the those traditions of the
royal families because the royal
families were wiped out most of them.
the real ones in 1857.
So the Marata Empire was so powerful in
the entire subcontinent. What happened
to it? No power, no influence, no
existence today. The Roman Empire was
all powerful
across the Mediterranean region, across
Europe, across North Africa, even parts
of West Asia. What happened to it? Gone.
Right?
Look at Italy today. What power, what
influence does Italy have today? I'm not
trying to make fun of the nation. I'm
just giving you giving this example.
Okay. The Vikings were super powerful in
Western Europe. There was a Viking age
roughly 200 years. What happened?
Where's the Vikings today? Sweden,
Denmark, Norway. What about these three
nations? What power influence do they
have? None. [clears throat]
So the answer is that empires rise and
fall. Empires rise,
empires become powerful, then they
decline and they fall. It's these are
cyclical aspects of history. So the
Spanish Empire, you know, the Spanish
power came, grew and went. Their
policies weren't great. They weren't
able to eventually compete with the
Anglo, with the English. The same can be
said about Portugal and everybody else.
So,
so that's why today it's only the
Anglo-Saxon Empire that has the
hedgemony, you know, essentially global
power projection capabilities because
they got everything right.
Their system of financing their
operations and expeditions and their,
you know, yeah, expeditions of plunder
and conquest.
They were financed properly. They were
great at logistics. They were great at
playing a gate of game of divide in
rule, divide and rule, divide and
conquer and then rule. They were great
at securing uh trade routes.
They were great at securing choke
points, geographical choke points. The
Spanish and the Portuguese weren't great
at this. The Portuguese had this policy,
you could say, of just holding on to two
holes of land, footholds of foot to
having to having small footholds of
land,
you know, on the margins of the trade
routes and choke points like Mala, the
the Portuguese at Mala, the Portuguese
at Goa, they had Vasai in western India
uh and so on. So they they did not ever
expand inwards into the land into the
territory of the of the subcontinent or
other parts of the world. The British
said, "We're going to create our own
kingdoms. We're going to actually govern
land." The Portuguese didn't want to
govern anything. They just wanted to
trade and plunder. So the Spanish
obviously did what the British did, but
they were not as efficient, efficacious,
whatever, as the British. So that's why
the British eventually prevailed and
that's why Spain and Portugal are
essentially
well to be very realistic, non- entities
geopolitically today.
Amisha once again says why did the
Portuguese colonies in South America
evolve into a single country which is
Brazil whereas the continent's Spanish
colonies broke off into nearly a dozen
nations. Interesting question. Let's
take a look at the map and see the
situation in South America for with our
own eyes to confirm what Amisha is
claiming. So here we have one gigantic
nation, Portuguese speaking nation which
is Brazil and then you have all these
Spanish speaking nations like Argentina,
Chile, Peru, Ecuador, Colombia,
Venezuela
and then you have we'll not talk about
Guyana here. Uruguay, we forgot Uruguay,
Parag Paraguay, Bolivia. So all these
Spanish speaking nations and just one
Portuguese speaking nation. What
happened? How did this happen? Why did
the Portuguese colonies
evolve into a single nation, single
modern day nation, Brazil? But the
Portuguese colon uh the Spanish colonies
all gave rise to multiple nations that
actually weren't on very good terms with
each other. How did that happen is the
question.
So I spoke about the treaty of toias
1494. The Spanish and the Portuguese
divided the world into two halves. Okay.
and uh
and it was along a line see let's take a
look at um let's Google this so that I
can put this on the screen for easy
comprehension
tree of toa
1494 look at the images
so if you see okay let's see this as you
can see on the screen they divided the
world into two halves and the line on
the left as you can see It it kind of
uh gives
Portugal the the blue territory. It
gives Portugal what is now Brazil less
than what is Brazil today. But the
Portuguese were given the right to uh
occupy and colonize that part of the
Americas. Okay? Because of the line that
was drawn on the map. So the Brazilians
go the Portuguese go ahead and create
this colony. And what the Portuguese do
is they create a single viceroy for the
entire region.
But what the Spanish did is that they
created multiple territories that were
self-governing. You had New Spain, you
had uh whatever else the other other
ones were called. You had the what was
Peru and the Inca Inca Empire region and
so on. So they they the Spanish created
essentially autonomous
quasi independent self-governing
territories that would all report back
to Spain but they would not
but they were all autonomous in a way
from each other.
Okay. So that's how the Spanish
organized uh the territories they had uh
occupied in the Americas. The Portuguese
put everything under one single viceroy.
And for the Spanish there multiple
viceroy
and
these these Spanish colonies became kind
of competitive with each other also. So
there was you know there was a
safeguarding of territory and there was
a bit of friction and hostility and that
sort of thing between the different
Spanish territories. Even though they
were all Spanish territories they all
reported back to the you know to the
crown in Spain. But in in the case of
Brazil it was not the case. It was
everything was under a single viceroy.
Then you have so we're talking about
what the aftermath of 1494 1492 1494.
We're talking about we're talking about
the 1500s the 1600s and so on even the
1700s. So the situation evolves in this
manner. Okay. Then what happens is in
Europe something incredible happens. You
have the rise of this one person called
Napoleon Bonapart. Napoleon
in 19 years he went to a no from being
an absolutely obscure nobody to being
the emperor of France and king of Italy
in just 19 years. That's Napoleon.
Incredible feat. And he he he would do
over one weekend what most people would
do in their lifetime. That sort of
thing. reorganizing the entire uh
governance system of let's say a country
and writing a new constitution putting
new laws new governance and that sort of
thing u and Napoleon was very ambitious
and there was this period of time which
is called the Napoleonic wars in Europe
and he con he invaded Spain as part of
the Napoleonic wars we're talking about
the early 1800s 1805 to 1815 or is it
1803 to 1815 let's let's quickly take a
Nepo Leo Nick was when was this? 1803 to
1815. Okay, I was almost correct. Yeah,
you don't have to memorize dates. You
can look always look them up. So the
Napoleonic Wars is when Napoleon tried
to conquer the entire world starting
with Europe and he invaded Spain. As a
result of this, the Spanish colonies in
the Americas were kind of cut a drift
from the crown in Spain
and they became kind of independent
and that is the genesis of the
independent nations all Spanish speaking
nations in the Americas. So the
governors would they they were no longer
connected to Spain. Spain was in
complete disarray. Napoleon was invading
right and this completely changed the
structure and governance and so on of
Spain. So these colonies became
essentially independent and they became
nation states eventually on their own
right and some of them went to war with
each other that that happens that that
is known to happen in the in in Latin
America two nations may sometimes go to
war over a football match even though
they are both Spanish speaking that sort
of thing but Brazil did not happen. So,
uh, so Brazil becomes independent of
Portugal. What? In the 1820s.
When was it? Let's let's let's fact
check. What was the actual year? Let's
let's find out. Brazil independence
year
in. Okay, it's 1822. So, Brazil becomes
indep Oh, I'm sorry. I did not put that
on the screen. So Brazil becomes
independent from Spain or from Portugal
on the 7th of September 1822. Brazil
becomes independent. And then in Brazil
also it was not all smooth sailing.
There were parts of Brazil especially
northern or whatever that wanted to
secede that wanted to be independent.
And the Brazilian government had to use
military force for a couple of decades
to quell these rebellions and these
quests for for independence. So it was
not all smooth sailing but yeah Brazil
eventually was able to prevail uh and
that's how they were able to remain
united as a single nation Brazil whereas
the other continental
uh Spanish colonies broke off into a
bunch of other countries and the way the
they they b broke off into various
countries depends obviously on the
geography of the continent. You have the
Andes mountains which obviously
separates Peru and and and and Chile
from the rest from the from the eastern
part of the continent and so on.
Okay. Bill Bradley says what does Bill
Bradley say? Chingis Khan the great
Mongol conqueror ended enough lives to
leave a mark in the carbon record. He
was one of the most prolific takers of
life ever seen. This is the worst
academic channel on YouTube. Okay. So, u
I have in the past said that Chingis
wasn't that bad and so on. So, this
gentleman Bill Bradley says that I am
one of the worst academic channels on
YouTube and Chingish Khan killed so many
people that it left a mark in the carbon
record.
Let us find out whether I am completely
wrong and I'm completely biased and this
is the worst academic channel on
YouTube. Let's find out. Let's let's
fact check this. Okay. Um,
okay. Genghis Khan
carbon record global cooling. So it said
that he he caused global cooling, right?
So there is this website
Mongab. Okay. What is this if science?
Let's take a look at this. Okay. It says
that Chinus Khan killed enough planet
people to cool the planet. And this is
by whoever uh gentleman called Benjamin
Ta who holds a master's degree in
anthropology from University College
London and he has word worked in
neuroscience and mental health. Okay. So
this gentleman has a master's degree in
anthropology from University College
London. So he says
he says that scientists have identified
a certain decrease in atmospheric carbon
of about three parts per million. three
parts per million. Remember that between
1200 and 1470 CE which correlates with
the Mongol invasion of Asia and so on.
Um
and uh this may account for changes in
carbon dioxide levels and uh um allowed
more trees to grow and act as carbon
sinks and so on. Uh despite
D
um so okay so that's what he says. So he
says that Chingghis Khan killed enough
people to cool the planet. That is his
claim. And he has said that they
sequestered huge amounts of carbon
dioxide from the atmosphere possibly
even cooling the planet. So that is what
our friend uh what's his name Benjamin
Taub says and uh there is this mongabe
whatever that is which also makes the
same claim and uh how chistan cooled the
planet altered life sciences Mongol
invasion altered carbon dioxide levels
and so on. So this is a very commonly
believed
uh thing why Jungaskan was good for the
for the planet that's what the guardian
of the UK is saying and so on. Now let's
take a look at some actual
research papers. Yes. Um
so
so let's take a look at this one here.
Okay. This is from this is from the
astrophysical astrophysics data system.
This is actually something that is more
connected to well my field but it also
has this paper about carbon emissions.
So holosene carbon emissions is a result
of anthropogen anthropogenic land cover
change and the DOI
is the last six numbers are 386 983
386983 Now let me put the actual PDF on
the screen.
Okay, here let's open it. Let's let's
fact check this properly. Okay. Once
again it's the same D yeah DOI 386983
same paper. Yeah. So and then this is by
Kaplan Crumbheart Ellis Rimman etc etc
etc. These are the authors. Holosene
carbon emissions as a result of
anthropogenic land cover change. So here
we have a graph a chart. Let's bigify it
ambigen enlarge it.
So on the [snorts]
y-axis the vertical axis we have
atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration
and also human population in millions
and on the horizontal axis we have years
before present. So this ends at 1850.
Okay it starts at 6,000 years before
present. So if we look at the time
period of 2,000 years before present
that is you know when the ADBC shift
happens and
we're talking about 1200 to 1400 AD
right so it's around this time period 1
to 750 and you can see that there is the
the there are two graphs here two lines
the top one is the human population and
on the bottom the second lower one that
is the carbon dioxide levels in parts
per million atmospheric carbon dioxide
concentration in parts per million. And
as you can see between 1,00 before years
before present and 750 years before
present or even 500 years before present
there is no major
there's no major change in the
atmospheric carbon levels whatever
change happens it's just very minor very
gradual
right so chisan was born when 1170 or
something and he died in 1227 so around
that time what do you see and afterwards
also the Mongol empire was a very big
deal for the next century or so you see
no such thing here. You don't see any
major change in the uh you know
atmospheric carbon dioxide uh
concentration.
So that kind of raises a question mark
about what these people have been
claiming. Now let's try take a look at a
different research paper and it's
verifying that we are human here. We are
all humans. Yes, I would confirm that
coupled climate carbon simulations
indicate minor global effects of wars
and epidemics on atmospheric carbon
dioxide between so and so between 800 AD
and 1850. So let us put the PDF of this
research paper on the screen. It's by
Julia Pongrats at Aal Julia Pongrats all
same paper. Okay. Now let's take a look
at what this paper claims.
Let's embigen it. So it says okay only
the Mongol invasion could have lowered
global carbon dioxide but by an amount
too small to be resolved by ice.
So they're talking about
the reduction of global carbon dioxide
levels. They say that the Mongol
invasion only could have lowered it but
it would have been by an amount that is
too small to be resolved by eye scores.
Now let's let's go down
and let's take a look at whatever the
paper is all about. Let's let's take a
look at some details. So it it's talking
about global carbon dioxide decreases.
This global decrease in carbon dioxide
caused by the Mongol invasion is still
smaller than 0.1 parts per million and
therefore not detectable in eye score
records with a typical measurement
precision of one part per million. Okay.
Now let's ask. So clearly the claims
don't hold up. Now let's ask Google to
fact check. Okay, please fact fact
check.
Genghis Khan
in end did enough lives to uh leave
leave
a mark
on the carbon
record. Please fact check. What's it
say? What does the Google AI say? It
says nothing.
So, as you can see, okay, how about I
try
a different version of Google.
Let's try a different version of Google.
Give me a second, please. Let's try a
diff different version. One where I'm
logged in. Now, let's say what happens
now. I'm going to ask it to fact check.
Okay, it's a once again not the Google
AI isn't. Where is the AI? Okay, let's
go. Let's go to AI mode. Please fact
check this. What's the what does the
Google AI say? This claim is based on
2011 study from Canada blah blah blah
which key findings from the research
include blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah. Um, okay.
Where does it come from? It's giving me
social media stuff.
Um,
please please please
find the link to the study.
Okay, please come on, bro. Let's do it.
Does it have a link? Julia Pong. Okay,
we just opened that document, the the
document, the study by Julia Pongrats.
Aal, right? So according to that
research paper
one second let me just copy paste this
okay uh the research paper says
and I quote
in quotes
right is still smaller
So does the claim that Genghis
ended?
So yeah.
So does the
claim still hold up?
One second. What does this say?
Right. Okay. So, so
was
was there was was there any measured?
So, is there any evidence? Okay. Is
there
any actual
[clears throat]
uh empirical
evidence of
uh decrease
in
CO2
levels due
to a due to the Mongol invasion?
Mongol
invasion.
Please answer in one word.
Let's see what's it says. Thinking
no empirical evidence suggests a
decrease in carbon dioxide levels due to
Mongol invasion. I could go into this in
great detail, but I think I just
debunked
this claim, this malicious claim that
Shinkasan killed so many people that
there were there was a global decrease
in carbon dioxide levels and global
cooling. I just debunked this right in
front of you.
This is how narratives are built.
The research paper clearly says there is
no no measurable decrease and whatever
decrease we are imagining is is is
inferred or imagined or whatever
there is no hard evidence of any
measurable decrease in global carbon
dioxide to levels from that time period.
I just debunked this live for you all.
So this is how people create narratives.
This is how the west creates narratives
about the east. That is how they have
managed to globally demonize Chingish
Khan.
Okay, I just debunked this live in front
of you. You can please feel free to go
deeper into this. You will find zero
evidence, no evidence whatsoever, no
hard scientific evidence whatsoever from
ice scores or whatever other means you
want to look into. There's no evidence
whatsoever that there was any decrease
in global carbon dioxide levels or or
there was any global cooling whatsoever
because of any Mongol invasion. There
you have it. All right.
Victor Knight says, "Was the Mongol
Empire destructive or was it a cause or
a catalyst of globalization?"
Look, an empire that expands is going to
cause destruction. I mean look at world
history. You can't say that you can't
expect one empire to somehow be
non-destructive. The Mongol Empire, you
know, it expanded for a variet variety
of reasons. It starts with Chingghis
Khan. It starts with the Sha of Horas
and his treatment of Mongol
diplomats and merchants. Horrible
treatment. So that had to be dealt with.
Before that it was all about China and
China's brutal treatment of Mongolia for
centuries. That's how the entire
expansion started. Okay. So the Mongol
Empire became a very large empire. It
essentially you could say that Chinghan
possessed possessed half of the world
known world of its of of his time and
after his death the Mongol empire
expanded even further because of the
conquests of his sons and grandsons and
so on. His grandson Hullegu ended the
golden age of Islam for example by
by flattening Baghdad. So the Mongol
Empire obviously it expanded through
military conquest. It caused
destruction. It may have caused the
deaths of potentially millions of
people. But if you calculate the number
of deaths per square kilometer, I would
say Timour will go higher, the Romans
will go higher, Alexander will go
higher, the British Empire will go
higher in in the metric that I'm talking
about which is number of deaths per
square kilometer. Chinghan will be lower
than them all. I I don't have the
numbers right now. I could actually do
this. I'll not do it live because it'll
take half an hour at least to get the
data and stuff. But I can guarantee that
the number of lives how many lives are
attributed to Ching Khan. Whatever the
number is, it's going to be lower than
Timur or the Turk invasions of India and
so much more. So let's not discuss go
into that. Now what about the Mongol
Empire being a cause or a catalyst of
globalization? So the Mongol Empire
unified essentially half of Eurasia
maybe yeah roughly half of Eurasia
Eurasia which is parts of Europe and
much of Asia excluding the Indian
subcontinent. Uh Chunghistan decided he
will not invade India because he had no
reason to and I've gone into that in my
first video in detail. So the Mongol
Empire it created a unified Eurasian
zone. Okay. Um and the Mongols were very
much in favor of uh having trade
across the entire Mongol Empire. So u
they they established what they called
caravan suravan sarise. They established
relay stations. They gave diplomats and
other people passports. They
standardized weights and measures across
their entire kingdom. and they ensure
that there are relatively predictable
taxes across the entire empire. So
suddenly the entire empire this huge
part of Eurasia becomes open. There are
no more boundaries and borders and all.
You could just go in any if you were a
citizen of the Mongol Empire you could
travel anywhere as long as you had a
valid business. So it created a huge
essentially free trade zone with very
clear predict predictable rules and all
the infrastructure you needed to travel
and to do trade. And this had the effect
of of of stimulating
uh and catalyzing cross-cultural
exchanges because you had so many
because you
this
caused the the creation of this huge
infrastructure, trade infrastructure
caused the movement it it it facilitated
it facilitated the movement of scholars,
of craftsmen, of artisans, of religious
figures
of technicians of scientists, engineers,
writers,
poets, singer, whatever all kinds of
people across Eurasia. So this catalyzed
cross-cultural exchanges. So it created
a huge free trade zone. It catalyzed
cross-cultural exchanges across the
entire empire and it linked the the
economy of China with Central Asia with
the Islamic world and with even parts of
the Eurasian with the parts of the
various European economies all because
everything was protected by the Khan the
great Khan. So clearly this is one of
the first examples of globalization,
proper globalization under a clear and
predictable system of rules, a
rules-based world order, wasn't it? So
yeah, it was indeed a catalyst of
globalization,
right? Okay.
Nirvana Shanks says, "How did Nirvana
Shanks has asked a lot of questions, but
you asked at the very end just a couple
of hours before the live stream, so I
was able to take only one, but maybe
I'll take some of some more of your
questions in the next uh episode." So
the question here is this, how did
Chancellor Bismar unify Germany and what
were the major consequences for the
European balance of power? Right,
Germany. So Germany is well historically
the past century or so it's been the
engine that drives the European economy.
It's the most historically we know it's
been you could say the most powerful
nation in Europe until 1945 you could
say right but Germany as a nation
it it was born in 1871
before that there was never something
called Germany. The Romans spoke about
various Germanic tribes,
the Swaybe and the whatever the
[clears throat] names of the tribes
were. There was never a unified German
nation. There were various Germanic
speaking
well, you know, states you could say,
duchies and and so on, principalities
and so on, but it was never one unified
nation called Germany. So bismar so
there was something called Prussia.
Prussia was this major um major you
could say
German speaking principality in what is
now Germany. So Bismaron Bismar was
Prussian and he was appointed in the
1860s as the minister president of
Prussia. Okay. If you want to see where
is Prussia, what what used to be
Prussia? Let's uh let's first take a
look at that. What was Prussia?
[clears throat]
Prussia. So let's uh go to images and
this was Prussia essentially. Okay, the
the green part which is obviously kind
of part of much of Germany today. That
was Prussia. This the here's another
example of Prussia.
This is from 1867 to 1871 before the
war. So we will talk about that now. So
that was Prussia and Ottoan Bismar
became the uh minister president of of
Prussia in the 1860s and he said that
we're going to unify the land through
blood and iron through strategy strategy
and real politic. So then he engineered
three wars of unification. Okay. The
first war was the Danish war. He went to
war with he what what what what Bismar
did is that he allied with Austria. He
allied with Austria and fought Denmark
and defeated Denmark and and they took
the Danish then Danish territories of
Schleswig and Holstein
and that became part of you know their
territory
and then he went to war with Austria
with whom he had allied against Denmark.
So first in the 1860s there's a war with
uh Denmark which which Prussia and
Austria win. Then Prussia goes to war
against Austria. Um he provoked some he
he found some protects some excuse to go
to war with Austria. He allied himself
with Italy. He ensured that the French
and the Russians remained neutral and
then he went to war with Austria and
defeated Austria. And then he
marginalized Austria. He he essentially
excluded Austria from German affairs
altogether and uh the old confederation
and old alliance was invalidated or or
dissolved. So he defeats Austria and
then there's the pivotal war 1870 1871
the FrancoRussian war. So now that
Austria is dealt with [clears throat]
right he now goes to war. He he goss
France into declaring war against
Prussia. And then he says that they are
facing an existential threat. France is
going to defeat us all. So he rallies
all the other southern German
principalities into an alliance with
Prussia to uh defeat the French and they
are able to defeat the French and there
is a very harsh treaty that is imposed
on the French and the French territory
Al-Sas and Loren is taken into Germany
is is annexed into Germany and by doing
this he was able to consolidate and
create a unified Germany by through
these three wars first with Denmark then
with Austria then with the And that's
how he was able to you know create this
common cause for all the German
principalities that we have to we have
to come together uni unified unify and
unite otherwise we'll be taken apart and
that's how he was able to create a
unified Germany. So 1871 is the creation
of the German empire.
Prussia under bismar br b br b br b b b
b b b b b b b b b b b b b b b b b b b b
b b b b b b b b b b b b b all southern
principalities and states and duchies
into a new federal structure which was
dominated by Berlin. Okay. And then he
pro then they proclaimed Wilhelm the
first as the German empire in Vai in
France. It was in 1871
and the entire thing was structured in
such a way that Prussia was essentially
in control of uh various aspects of
administration and the major power in
what was now Germany especially power
over the army military policy foreign
policy economic policy all of that. So
the unification of Germany was a triumph
of Bismar. It was a tri triumph of
Prussian power and it was a triumph of
German nationalism. So how did this what
kind of consequences did this have on
Europe is the question that Nirvana
Shanks is asking? What were the
consequences uh for Europe? So the see
you suddenly have in 1871 the creation
of a new German Empire, a new nation of
Germany and a German empire. this new
nation. It has a large population. It
has advanced industry. It has a
a tremendously excellent education
system. It has this laser focus on on on
on technology and science. I mean,
quantum mechanics comes out of Germany,
right? Doesn't it? And they had because
of because they had an advanced
industry, high quality industry. Because
of that, they also had a first rate
military.
And Germany essentially almost overnight
became the leading
terrestrial or land power in Europe. And
it became a major industrial economy and
a major uh and and the leader in science
and technology and engineering and and
everything else in Germany.
And because of this excellent education
system, it eventually gave gave the
world tremendously gifted physicists who
changed the way we understand the world.
Okay. And Austria was permanently
excluded uh from from German politics.
It was it was marginalized and it was
relegated to a regional role within a
dual monarchy which is AustriaHungary
the Austrohungarian Empire right and it
it weakened Austria significantly. Uh
France almost lost also
France was humiliated. it lost prestige
and this obviously gave rise to this
desire for revenge within the people of
France and this became you could say a
long-term persistent source of enmity
with this new nation of Germany and the
unification of this new nation Germany
it forced various other powers like
Russia and everybody else to look for
look towards creating their own
alliances
uh because the rise of strong,
confident, very powerful New Germany. It
obviously led to the intensification of
arms races and rivalries with uh with
obviously France, with with Russia, with
Italy and AustroHungary and so much
more.
So you had tension and eventually
obviously Britain. Yeah, Britain also
was as you know it was the British Raj
the British Raj. of the creation of this
new nation, it obviously would be seen
as worrisome from England and all these
factors,
all these simmering rivalries and
hostilities,
they became the melting point, melting
pot and the could say the key factors
that eventually pushed Europe towards
what would be called the first world
war. So yeah, it it set in motion a
series of events that gave rise to the
first world war. So the period between
1871 and 1914 you could say was a period
of cold war where everybody was looking
for an advantage and everyone was
looking for the day we could we can go
back to war and
settle old scores. So that was the deal.
Chancellor of Bismar unifying Germany
and eventually this eventually all
culminated in the first world war which
did not end end end satisfactoryily for
Germany which gave rise to the second
world war and the rest we understand
says explain the origins of the Romans
that built the Roman Empire were the
European in the modern sense perfectly
white skin I'm not sure if Europeans
have perfectly white skin but some
Europeans I suppose you could say are
very white skin. Okay. So, what's the
origins of the Roman people? Who founded
the Roman Empire? First, first of all,
let's look at the map to talk to to
understand what part of the world are we
talking about? The Roman Empire emerged
from Italy. So, it's in the
Mediterranean region, southern Europe.
Italy is this place. And the region
around the city of Rome is where you had
this uh Latin speaking group of people
um who became the founders, you could
say, of Rome. And there are mythological
factors in this and there's legends
associated with this the legend of
Reheis and Rmulus. Uh it is also said
that Rome was founded by by Greeks who
fled from the Trojan war and so on. U so
north of the region of present day Rome
you had another ethnic group that lived
there. They were called the Atruscans.
And in the south you had ethnic Greeks
who lived in the southern parts of
Italy. uh which was you could say you
know greater Greece region kind of
thing. So the the people who eventually
beca who founded Rome as a republic they
lived in the region around Rome and then
they intermarried with the atruscans and
with the with the with the ethnic Greeks
who lived in southern Rome and it became
kind of a mixed population. What was the
ethnicity? It was a southern European
ethnicity which means light brown skin
not exactly white skin. Yeah. And
eventually as we know Rome became an
empire and they conquered
the Celtic parts of Europe which is Gaul
which is today's France and Switzerland.
They conquered the the the Iberian part
of of Europe which is present day Spain.
The Spanish people also don't really
have white skin. Uh they conquered North
Africa uh where the people cannot really
be called white people. They obviously
aren't white. They aren't really black.
They're kind of brown, light brown. Um
they conquered eastern present day
eastern Europe, Romania, Bulgaria,
Thrace, Greece and so on. They conquered
Anatolia which is present day mostly
Turkey. They conquered West Asia also
and Egypt also and Northern Africa,
Libya and so on. And the people of this
entire huge region
most of them yeah they were then
regarded as Roman citizens and they were
free to move around the empire and then
the people in people intermixed and
inter intermingled. So you know so what
did the Roman people look like? The core
Roman people they would have had kind of
light brown skin. They would not be
white. They would have dark hair and
dark eyes mostly. Eventually, if you
look at Italy today, if you look at
Italian people today, many of them have
blonde hair and blue eyes. I mean,
Madame Melon, Georgia Melon has blonde
hair and blue eyes. So, her ancestry
probably lies north of Italy.
Yeah. Because Yeah. Because there was
intermixing of populations.
uh but the and you know what's
interesting is is that the Romans had
emperors who were of North African
origin, Arabic origin, Syrian origin.
[snorts] Septimus Severis was of Libyan
or Punic origin. He can be called the
first Roman emperor who was of African
origin. There was another one called
Mccrinus. Macrinus mccrinus whatever
these are all in the
Mrinus was from the 3rd century AD.
Septimus Severis was from the second and
third centuries AD. Then there was an
emperor called Philip the Arab who was
uh of Syrian descent. His family was
from present day Syria. And then you
also had an emperor called Elagavalus,
probably the worst Roman emperor of all
time who also was of Syrian origin.
So eventually the Romans became a very
cosmopolitan homogeneous kind of people
population. But the original Romans were
southern Europeans, which means that
they would have light brown skin, dark
hair, and and brown eyes mostly.
Okay.
Next question is by Amisha.
Why did the Roman Empire persecute early
Christians when they were mostly
content, the Romans, they were mostly
content to let the Jewish people
practice their faith with relatively
little interference? You were right. The
Romans ruled over Judea, which is
present day Israel. That Israel,
greater Israel or whatever region, West
Asia. Most people there practiced
Judaism. And the Romans, they had no
issue with Judaism. They did not
interfere with the Jewish activities,
religious activities. They only had an
issue when the Jews revolted against
Rome. And that's why as as a punitive
measure, they destroyed the second
temple, the Romans, right? And only one
wall stands, which is now called the
Whailing Wall. It's also one of the
walls of the Al Aka Moscow complex. Long
story, long story short. So the Romans
were perfectly happy to allow the Jews
to practice Judaism. They would they did
not interfere in that. The Romans never
interfere in Judaism. So then what was
the deal with Christianity?
You see, Judaism was an ancient
religion. It predated Rome
and the religion posed no threat
to the Roman Empire.
This was not a proletizing religion. The
the Jews not did not seek to
aggressively and actively convert people
to Judaism. And the religion was not a
political religion that that sought to,
you know, seek out and acquire and
consolidated power to do a regime
change. That sort of thing wasn't there.
Judaism was not that sort of religion.
It was an old religion and the people
practiced it and they they were not
political in nature. The religion wasn't
political in nature. So the Romans had
no issue with Judaism. whatsoever.
When it comes to Christianity, this was
a new artificial religion.
Okay? And this was a political religion.
The Christians sought to convert others
to Christianity. They sought to expand
their numbers and they sought to grab
power.
This was a totally different beast, a
completely new artificial cult
that was expansionist.
It did not simply seek to expand in
terms of territory. It sought to expand
its numbers by converting people. It
sought to destroy the old religion, the
Roman polytheistic religion. It
portrayed the Roman polytheistic
religion as evil, as satanic.
The Christians were brutal towards
polytheists. They were brutal towards
polytheistic
temples. They destroyed idols of Greek
and Roman gods and goddesses.
They desecrated temples. They they
killed priests. They killed
mathematicians, women mathematicians.
The Christians sought to overthrow Rome.
And then the Christians portrayed
themselves as the victims, martyrs.
So that's why the Roman Empire sought to
put an end to this. But as we know, it
didn't work out. And eventually the
Roman emperor Constantine converted to
converted to Christianity and made
Christianity the official state religion
because if you can't beat them, join
them. That's what happened.
Amisha says, "Why don't we know with
certainty how the Egyptian pyramids were
built? Was none of this information
passed down from generation to
generation?" So what are the pyramids
we're talking about?
Uh the pyramids of Egypt.
Egypt. [snorts] Pyramids of Egypt. So
these are world famous structures. I
think everyone knows what the pyramids
are. The pyramids are situated right
outside of Cairo. Aluk Kaira. And you
have uh three large pyramids of Giza and
then you have multiple smaller pyramids.
And as you can see, here is an image of
a human person
in in in comparison with the blocks that
make up the pyramids. As you can see,
the blocks are gigantic. This is clearly
an averagesized human person here.
[laughter]
Okay. Um the pyramids are gigantic and
these are some of the pyramids that we
have. The pyramid of Kufu, the pyramid
of Kafre, the manor pyramid, the red
pyramid, etc., etc., etc. So, the
pyramids are huge. You can't compare
them with any existing structures, any
existing buildings. Enormous, gigantic,
ginormous, whatever word you want to
call it. Uh what about the pyramid of
man? Let's say the pyramid of men.
So this pyramid as you can see has a
gigantic gaping hole in it. And the son
of Saladin Salahadin Aubi his son tried
for one year to destroy the small
pyramid. The pyramid of Manaw is a
reasonably small pyramid as you can see.
It's not huge. And the son of Saladin
who was ruling at the time, he tried for
one year to press his entire military
might into destroying this pyramid. All
he could do was create this one little
gash in the pyramid. That's all. Took
him one year. His his armed forces, his
soldiers were hard at work for one year
trying to destroy the pyramid. All they
did was make that little incision in the
pyramid.
They were all all they were trying to do
is take out the dislodge the blocks
those those those
uh cubicle blocks of stone and drop them
from from the pyramid. That work took
them one year to make that little
incision in the pyramid. And then you
have pyramids that are way bigger than
the manower pyramid. And how were they
constructed is the question. Now we kind
of have possibly some understanding. It
was not aliens. It was not UFOs. It was
obviously done by human beings. Tens of
thousands of slaves possibly worked on
the pyramids. It would have taken
possibly years or decades to build one
pyramid. And they would have used ramps,
clay ramps to to to transport each
individual stone block up the pyramid in
place into position. How did they do it
so precisely? Nobody has an idea. So
this is a these are works of monumental
architecture bigger than anything anyone
has done. It would have taken incredible
amounts of human labor, incredible
precision and decades of work to make
one pyramid.
And we if you were to make build a
pyramid today using modern equipment,
I'm not sure how it would be done. We
don't have cranes that can lift blocks
that blocks of store that large. We
don't have the means of possibly we do
how to align everything so precisely and
it's kind of it it's kind of
mindboggling. We probably don't have any
company or any organization today that
can if we you know if I give the money
okay here's $25 billion go and make a
pyramid in next 5 years. I don't think
they can do it even in the next 20
years. That's so hard.
Quarrying the stuff. How do you quarry
the rock and and ensure each block of
rock is exactly the right precise
dimensions? You would need metal tools,
probably copper tools that the copper
came from where the copper came from.
What metal did they use? So big open
questions remain. And and in case some
of the information was written down, it
would have been written down on papiras.
Papiras was the kind of parchment or
whatever you want to call it. The the
papyrus is a reed that grows on the
along the banks of the of the Nile and
that is purposed that is converted into
a sort of paper that was used in ancient
Egypt. Now papus is obviously fragile,
delicate. It can't last centuries or
thousands of years or millennia. That's
why if records were kept they would have
crumbled into dust by now. And
eventually Egypt was Egypt had a
downfall. It was first conquered by the
Persians for a while then it was
conquered by the Greeks. It was ruled by
the Greeks and then it came under um
under the rule of Islamic forces and
it's the entire population was converted
to Islam and today they don't even
regard the pyramids as anything really
important personally from their
perspective. It's important only because
it brings in tourist touristic revenue.
So eventually I think uh the records
were lost. people stopped carrying.
People started seeing that seeing the
pyramids as uh pre-Islamic
pagan monuments that should be destroyed
but could not be destroyed because they
were too hard to destroy and the they
was just tolerated until they became
a source of touristic revenue
and that's why we don't know for
certainty with certainty
how the pyramids were built.
Okay, let's talk about England. Nirvana
Shanks says another question. Were there
conflicts [snorts] between the Angles
and the Saxons after these ethnic groups
settled in England or did these ethnic
groups fully integrate into a single
political entity?
So, we're talking about England, the
British Isles.
The British Isles were under Roman
occupation until
roughly the 4th century AD.
Eventually the western Roman Empire
which was based out of which was ruled
from Rome it eventually declined and the
Romans eventually withdrew from England
from the British islands because it was
too far away and they could not they
didn't have the money to administer it
all. So they simply withdrew and once
the Romans withdrew they withdrew
sometime around the fourth or fifth
century around the time the transition
period between the two centuries around
the time the Romans withdrew. Let's
quickly Google this. When did the It was
When did the When did the Romans uh
withdraw
from Yeah. from Britain?
Which year was it?
Okay. AD410, which is the beginning of
the fifth century AD. And that created a
power vacuum in what we now call
Britain. Power vacuum. The imperial
force is gone. The imperial power is
gone. Rome is gone. This power vacuum.
So something has to fill the power
vacuum. It was the angles, the Saxons
and the Judes, these Germanic tribes
who filled the power vacuum. So the
these the Saxons came from the region of
Saxony in Germany.
The Angles came from another part of
Germany and the Jews also came were also
a Germanic tribe. So the angles and the
Saxons were the major population groups
that invaded Britain and settled in
Britain and the Judes also settled in
the southern part of Britain. So if you
look at the population of Britain at the
time it was a mixed it was mainly a
Celtic population.
The original inhabitants of Britain
around the time of the Roman occupation
were Celtic peoples, pictish people, you
know, various Celtic ethnic groups and
tribes.
Then the Angles and the Saxons and and
the Judes come in and then they fight
they they they defeat the Celtic peoples
and they establish various kingdoms in
uh Britain. What did these kingdoms look
like? Let's let's uh let's take a look.
Okay, let's take a look at a map of
Britain in let's say 8th century.
Map of Britain
in let's say 9th century.
What did Britain look like in the 9th
century AD? So now if we look here
um
do we have something from Encyclopedia
Britannica?
Okay so we have various kingdoms. Okay
as you can see on the map there is North
Umbria in the north you have the you
have Muria you have East Anglia Sex
Wessex Sussex Kent
then then you have Wales and Cumbria and
so on. So
the angles they set up the kingdom of
East Anglia
uh possibly Kent
um that's the angles and the Saxons
they set up North Umbrea Muriel Wessex
Sussex etc.
So the the westx is western saxons. SX
is the eastern Saxons. Sex is the
southern Saxons. Was North Umbria
was it Saxon or was it was North
Umbria?
North Umbrea. Saxon or Angle. Yeah,
there we go. It probably was
not Anglo. Okay, fine. So the point I'm
making is the angles and Saxons they
settled down in different parts of
Britain. The roots were all the way down
south. Essex, Sussex, Wessex were Saxon.
Probably North Umbrea etc. and and Muria
etc were
were settled by the angles.
But the deal is that the Angles and the
Saxons did not fight each other. When
these separate kingdoms were set up, it
did not matter anymore whether these
were Saxon kingdoms or angle kingdoms.
Even two angle kingdoms would have
differences and they would fight each
other each other at times. So it no
longer mattered once they settled down
and formed these kingdoms who was angle
and who was Saxon. Each kingdom was a
rival of the other and that was the
deal. So there was no Angles versus
Saxon kind of conflict or angles versus
Saxons versus Judes kind of conflict.
It did not matter at all once the
kingdoms were set up and you had
different kings who ruled these
different kingdoms. The kings would look
at each other king as a potential rival.
Sometimes there were war, sometimes
there were alliances as is always the
case.
Then you have the Viking age.
So at the time Wales remained a separate
entity more Celtic Welsh and the
Scottish etc were a separate entity and
so on. Then you have the Viking age. The
Vikings start
plundering, invading, raiding,
plundering the east coast of the British
islands of of Britain
and
because of that all these kingdoms have
to unify, unite in in a sense and fight
the Vikings.
So that gave rise to an Anglo-Saxon
identity which was separate from the
Viking identity and eventually gave rise
to an English identity
as opposed to Viking identity or or
Welsh or Scottish or Irish identity. So
eventually the Angles, Saxons and Judes
they they merged over time into a single
Anglo-Saxon or English identity and
ethnicity. And then you had the Norman
invasion in the year 1066 AD.
So it's it's been a long period of
upheaval in England and eventually it
all coaleses into one single uh ethnic
ethnic identity.
Swami says what caused the Norman
invasion of England in 1066 AD? Did
Harold Goodwinson Godwinson actually
break his oath or is the biotapestry
just Norman propaganda?
First of all, what is the biotopestry?
Bayou is a is a town in France. Okay,
Bayou is a town in the western part,
northwestern part of France. Normandy,
if we open the map, okay, it won't show
us too much detail. Maybe it will. Let's
zoom out.
So, here we have bio is on the west
coast of France. Okay. And let us now do
that. Yeah. So the bioapestry is this uh
biotapestry. Now
yeah very famous stunning 11th century
embroidered light linen 70 m long that
visually narrates the Norman conquest of
England in 1066 AD ending with the
battle of Hastings. And this is what it
looks like. And is it propaganda? Well a
lot of it is propaganda. Obviously it is
the Norman version of events of what
happened the entire story.
So who was Harold Goodwinson?
He was um he was the king of England in
the year 1066 AD. Now what oath are we
talking about and so on? That's a long
story, right? So Harold Goodwinson's
father.
No,
it was Edward the Confessor who was the
king of England before Harold
Goodwinson.
And Edward the Confessor died without
leaving a male hair.
Edward the Confessor was the son of Ethl
II.
Ethl Red II was king of England until he
was ousted
by the Vikings.
King Kenut of the was Viking. He invaded
England, kicked out King Award II and
ruled England for a you know ruled what
is now Britain for a for for a few
decades. And after Canututh was king,
his sons were kings of various parts of
England. One was uh Arthur Canut, the
other was Harold Herafoot.
Harold Airford or something. Yeah,
probably Harold Heroot.
So when
Ethel Red was sent into exile,
his son Edward the Confessor was also in
in exile.
And eventually once the once the
Viking age you could say ended or once
the Viking rule over England once uh
once Kenut is dead and his sons are no
longer in power either Haraka Canututh
or or or Harold Herfoot that's when
Edward the Confessor comes back to
England and the nobility of England they
elect him the king the nobility was of
England who actually elected kings was
called the whiten
Whiten or whiten a gamut or something?
Whiten gamut
game.
Yeah. Whitenagot.
It was a supreme council in Anglo-Saxon
England. Assembly of wise men,
highranking nobles, church leaders who
advise the kings of laws and blah blah
blah blah blah. The third thing. So they
elected Edward the Confessor as the king
of England. So Edward the Confessor
becomes a king and he Edward the
Confessor was in exile while the while
the Vikings were ruling England. Edward
the Confessor's mother was Norman.
And that's why Edward was in Normandy.
Okay, in exile. And while Edward the
Confessor was in Normandy in exile, he
apparently allegedly
made a promise to William of Normandy,
William the Bastard as he was then
known. So allegedly Edward made a
promise to William, the Duke of
Normandy, that he will give William the
crown of England.
And later Harold Goodwinson was also in
exile in Normandy for a few years. And
it is alleged that he also had made a
promise on some holy sacred relics that
he would make William the Duke of
Normandy the next king of England.
So Edward becomes king of England and
William does nothing but Edward dies
without a male hair. So the whitening
gamut once again comes together and they
appoint Harold Goodwinson as the king of
England in the year 1066 AD.
Now William of Normandy says that this
is all wrong because Harold has promised
me the crown of England. But the point
is that Harold did not have the right or
the authority to give the crown to
somebody. He was elected the king by the
whiten and as such he had to serve his
his his kingdom. He did not have the
authority to give the crown to somebody
else but whatever. So
so William of Normandy the Duke of
Normandy he got the pretext for war and
he also somehow secured the the support
of the Vatican.
So he then had assembled a big navy
which could cross the English Channel
and he crossed the English Channel in
1066 AD and then there's this war.
Harold Goodwinson, my goodness, what a
guy he was. So in the year 1066 AD,
Harold Goodwinson is has just been
appointed the king of England a while
ago and he gets news that in the north
part of England there's this huge Viking
invasion force that has landed.
And who is who who is leading the
Vikings? It is King Harold Hardrada
and Tostig Goodwinson, the brother of
Harold Goodwinson, traitor.
So Harold goes all the way north to
fight Tostig, his brother Tostig and
King Harold Hadra. He defeats them,
kills them both. It is what it is. It's
brutal battle. The battle of Stamford
Bridge 1066 AD. The battle is just over.
His army is beaten, bruised, but they're
victorious. And he gets the news
that William of Normandy has landed in
South England around Hastings. So then
he has to go all the way from the north
of England, march his army all the way
south, his beaten bruised army, and then
they meet then his army meets William of
Normandy in Hastings. And because of bad
luck or whatever, V Harold is killed by
an arrow to his eye and William becomes
victorious and he goes from being called
William the bastard to being called
being called William the Conqueror. So
that is the story
of the Norman invasion of England in
1066 AD.
Somi says, "Can you tell the story of
Henry II? How did Henry's knights
accidentally interpret his words and
kill Thomas Beckett? Henry II
interesting person. What was the the
words? Will nobody rid me of this
medalsome priest? That's what he had
said. So who was Henry II? So like I
said there was an invasion of England by
the Normans by William of Normandy in
the year 1066 AD. William the Conqueror.
He had multiple sons. His last son, the
youngest son, the eighth ling was Henry.
Henry Bclair and he was known as Henry
the first. He became the king of England
after the death of William Rufus, his
older brother
who died in the New Forest. Hunting
accident. Convenient. So Henry be Henry
the first becomes the king of England.
And
he had a crown prince who died in the
sinking of the white ship which was
crossing the English Channel. Because of
which his daughter Matilda became his
hair and she became the empress of
England.
So Matilda's son was Henry II. Henry II
was the grandson of Henry the
great grandson of William the Conqueror.
So Henry II was born in what is now
France. Okay. His father was Joffrey of
Onu and his mother was Empress Matilda,
daughter of Henry I.
So Henry II was the Duke of Normandy and
he was a great conqueror. Okay. He
married Eleanor of Akiten and he because
of which Akiten was a part of France and
Spain and so on and this and and he
waged many wars and conquests and he
expanded his kingdom in France. Then he
became the king of England also because
his grandfather was the king of England.
And so he succeeded the current king of
England as the king of England. And then
he um fought multiple campaigns in uh in
Scotland, in Ireland,
also in France, in Wales also. And he
expanded his kingdom significantly, his
empire you could say. So he became a
major major ruler in western Europe and
he had I don't know how many children
seven eight children multiple sons and
all you know when you have this army of
entitled children who are all
descendants of William the conqueror and
all sons of the king every they all want
power and eventually there was a
rebellion his sons rebelled one of his
sons was who were his sons
there was king John the younger John,
there was Edward was it? There was
Richard. Richard who eventually was
known as Richard the Lionhe Heart and uh
so on multiple sons.
So there were two rebellions by his sons
that he had to put down. Okay. Repeated
quarrels with his sons especially
Richard Richard the first Richard the
Lionhe Heart and all that stuff. Right.
He was even even eventually defeated by
his son Richard and he that eventually
led to the death of Henry II. But what
about this person Thomas Beckett? So
[snorts] Henry II was a friend of Thomas
Beckett. Thomas Beckett was a churchman.
He was a he was a priest. Okay. So Henry
II appointed Thomas Beckett as his royal
chancellor in the 12th century AD. And
uh Beckett was a close friend, close
companion
of the king and he was very good at
serving the interests, the royal
interests of the king and because of
that the king was very pleased with
Thomas Beckett and then the king Henry
II appointed Thomas Beckett the as the
archbishop of Canterbury which is a very
major uh church title in England. Okay.
So Thomas Beckett was appointed by Henry
as the Archbishop of Canterbury.
But after this happened, Thomas Beckett
became
he kind of changed his tune and he
started placing the interests of the
church above the the the interests of
the crown
and that became a problem. He is now the
Archbishop of Canterbury, the the most
high ranking church official in England
and he's going up against the king. He's
putting the the interest of the church
and the principles of the of the church
above what the king wants. Um he wants
to control the clergy. He want to he
wants to control. So that makes him very
powerful, right?
And because of that Henry sent Thomas
Beckett into exile out of the country
and eventually there was some kind of
reconciliation between Beckett
and the king and he came back. But very
quickly the disputes once again flared
up between the two of them. Right? And
because of this Henry II was super
frustrated with Thomas Beckett. It is
said that one day in his court he just
said this aloud to nobody in particular.
He said will nobody rid me of this
medalsome priest?
Will nobody rid me of this medalsome
priest? So he did not say this to one
person in specifically. He just said
this aloud
and four of his knights,
they
heard these angry words and they
interpreted these angry words as a
command to act
and they went to the
to Canterbury and they assassinated
Thomas Beckett in the altar of the
cathedral or whatever it is over there
and that was the deal. That is how
[laughter]
the Archbishop of Canterbury Thomas
Beckett was assassinated by four knights
of Henry II who interpreted Henry's
words as the command to to assassinate
Thomas Beckett. So those words are very
famous today. Will no one rid me of this
troublesome, meddlesome, turbulent
priest?
So by seeing these words to nobody in
particular and by by framing what he
said as a question,
Henry II established plausible
deniability for any guilt of any guilt
because see his words led to the
assassination of the Archbishop of
Canterbury. But he can say that you know
what I just asked a question. I did not
issue an order to somebody. I did not
say this to anybody in in particular. I
just said this aloud out of frustration.
Will nobody get rid me of this
troublesome medalsome priest. Right? So
that's the story of Henry II and uh and
the assassination of Thomas Beckett.
Swami says what was the Magna Carta? Why
did the English crown accept such an
arrangement? Was it just something that
was for namesake or did the king really
lose absolute power after the Magna
Carta? What was the Magna Carta?
So we spoke about Henry II, right?
The great king of England, the great
king. Yeah. Of of Normandy as also his
son, his successor after Richard I was
John. King John of England.
Now Richard the first, Richard the Lion
Hard was this very vigorous warrior king
who was more interested in fighting than
ruling. So he spent his whole life
fighting and eventually he got killed
out of sheer stupidity or carelessness.
There's no need for him to get killed
the way he got killed. But that's a
different story. So Richard the
Lionheart is dead and then John comes to
power. His younger son of one of his his
younger brother sorry one of his
brothers John the son of Henry II. So
John was a weak king and uh he issued
this royal charter called the Magna
Carta. Okay, this royal charter, the
Magna Carta, it listed the king's powers
and by listing the powers of the king,
it limited the king's powers. And the
Magna Carta also ensured enshrined
affirmed certain customs, certain
liberties, certain privileges of the
church and also of the king's minions,
the king's baronss. So it essentially
was a written agreement between the
king, between King John and his baronss
who had rebelled against him. See, King
John, the son of Henry II, Henry the was
was great, was a great king. His son,
King John was a weak king and he was not
a good king. He wasn't a good
administrator. I mean, you can be
you can be a good administrator even if
you're not a great conqueror, right? But
he was not that. His rule was unpopular,
widely unpopular.
His taxation was heavy. The kind of
justice that he imparted was very
arbitrary.
He was a military failure. He lost most
of his father's French territories,
French French lands. His finances were
ruined. His prestige was
down the drain essentially. So that is
King John. And because he was a weak
king,
his his minions. See, every king has
nobles and baronss and all who serve him
who have their their own armies that are
to be
provided to the king on demand on on
demand whenever required that sort of
thing. That was the structure the feudal
structure the the the structure of you
know that part England and and Europe of
the time. So a number a group of his
baronss most powerful baronss they
rebelled against him with the backing of
the church. They organized a rebellion
against King John. And in the year 1215
they captured and occupied London which
obviously if you capture the the capital
of England of Britain it gives you a
tremendous amount of leverage. It gave
them a very
strong bargaining position. And once
this happened, the capture and
occupation of London, it essentially
meant civil war. Civil [snorts] war
became a real immediate threat, a real
clear and present danger for King John.
So the Archbishop of Canterbury,
obviously Thomas Beckett is dead by now.
So whoever was next or or whoever was
the Archbishop of Canterbury at the
time, he said, "I'll be a mediator." And
what he did was he supported the baronss
in what way? He took the baron's list of
demands. Okay? And he converted that
into a formal text, a formal charter
text that could serve as a peace
agreement, a peace settlement. And and
this this is something that uh King John
had to sign otherwise there would be
civil war and he would be defeated. So
this came to be known as the great
charter or the Magna Carta in Latin. And
this document essentially in this
document the king of England promises
all kinds of rights and privileges. The
pro protection of church rights, various
church rights, um protections from
unlawful imprisonment to to his minions,
to his baronss, technically his minions,
right? Um he promises reasonably swift
justice. Uh the charter limited various
kinds of taxes. You know what is the
maximum kind of tax the crown can can
impose and it also limited the amount of
payments that the baronss had to make to
the crown to the to the king of England.
So this listed down exactly what are the
the powers that the king has and by
doing that it curtailed his powers.
Okay, it curtailed his powers and yeah,
so this is where historians will tell
you that this is where you have a
properly codified the beginning of
properly codified codified rule of law
in England. But who benefited from this?
Did the people of England benefit from
this? They did not. Around this time,
90% 95% of the people were either
peasants or slaves.
It's only 5% which were the the king and
his knights and baronss and and the
military people and the church people.
Everybody else was oppressed. All
everybody was peasants or landless serfs
or slaves.
Did the 95% of the population did they
benefit? Did they gain did they gain
anything from the Magna Carta? Nothing
whatsoever. So who gained who benefited
from this? It was the baronss and the
church that benefited. So the rule of
law was for them.
No arbitrary injustice and arbitrary
justice and all that was for them not
for the common people. They continued to
be oppressed for the longest time. Now
they are free I suppose. So that's the
deal about the Magna Carta. Okay.
John Goodman says you claimed that the
white huns the hunas destroy the takashi
taxila. What is taxila? What is a taxa?
Are you talking about the takashila
university? It is not taxa. It is
takashila.
I refuse to use the barbaric
contraction taxula. It is takashila. So
I claimed the white hones the shueta
hunas destroyed the takshashila. But
there is quite strong evidence to
suggest that it was actually Alexander
the third of Macedon who did so. What
are your views on that? Okay,
look,
we don't have Indian records of the time
of Alexander's invasion of the western
fringes of India. We don't have any
Indian records that survive from the
time. But we do have Greek records of
Alexander's alleged um you know invasion
and rule or some parts of western India.
So according to Greeks, Greek records,
according to Greek historians,
chronicles from from a couple of
centuries after Alexander,
uh there was a king
who ruled in Takashila at the time. His
name was King Ambi.
The Greeks called him Taxile.
Taxile. And he was apparently a rival of
King Porus Purusam or whatever his name
was. And the Greeks claim that the king
of Praula,
King Ambi, voluntarily surrendered to
Alexander. He gave all his silver and
his wealth and his territory to
Alexander. Sir, you are so great. Please
take it all. Alexander was very pleased
with him. And he said, you keep their
wealth. You keep your kingdom, but you
serve me. So you are now my vasal. So
that's what the Greek records say that
the king of Pakashila, King Ambi or
Taxile
voluntarily surrendered to Alexander and
Alexander allowed him to keep his wealth
and his his territory. Let's see what
Wikipedia has to say about this.
King not Abi Ambi King Ambi. Uh you see
Wikipedia calls him Taxileles.
Taxileles or Taxilas was the Greek
chronicler's name for the ruler who who
reigned over the track between the Sundu
and the Jillum rivers in the Punjab
region at the time of Alexander's
expedition. His name was Ambi.
Um the Greeks appear to have called him
taxes or whatever after the name of his
capital city of Takshila near Atak
Pakistan. So that's what it the thing
claims and u
uh so apparently
Ambi sent an ambassador to Alexander
with presence of lot of silver and oxen
and sheep and he was on hostile terms
with his neighbor Porus and uh yeah so
he surrendered to Alexander. Alexander
returned Ambi's title and all that and
so on. So clearly
according to the Greek records Ambi
surrendered to Alexander and Alexander
did not destroy Tuxila did not kill
Ambi. He returned the kingdom to Ambi.
He said you keep the kingdom keep your
wealth you be my vasal and that's all I
need from you. And the Greek records
even claimed that Alexander went to the
university and and interacted with
gymnosophists or whatever that is which
is obviously uh Indian intellectuals
from the university and he was very
impressed with them and so on. So
according to Greek records Alexander
does not do any damage to the university
of Takshashila. Indian records are
silent about Alexander completely
completely silent about him and later
the region comes under various you know
various regimes.
Sometimes the region was temporarily
under Persian rule. Most of the time it
was under Indian rule. Then for some
time it came under Indo- Greek rule.
Then it came under skitian rule. Then it
came under Kushan rule. And eventually
it was overrun by the hunas and they
destroyed Takashila. One of their
ignorant kings destroyed Takashila. Was
it Mirul?
Possibly Mihir. Possibly. Yeah. So
that's that's what actually the records
tell us,
right?
Rahul Dunak says, "When did the concept
of high-rise buildings come to
existence?
high-rise buildings.
So, tall buildings. One great example of
really tall buildings from antiquity is
the pyramids of Egypt. Very tall. Very
tall. Very tall. But those aren't
high-rise buildings. These are not
buildings for human habitation. The
pyramids there their purpose is still
unknown what purpose they actually
served. So, they were not buildings.
They were monuments.
Which is the oldest known recorded
high-rise building? Possibly the
Kaneshka Stupa. Let's let's Google that.
How tall was that? So that's about from
roughly 1900 years ago.
It is now lost. The Pakistanis have
destroyed it.
Okay. So outskirts of Peshawar. What
does the what does Wikipedia say about
this? As always, Wikipedia is not a
reliable source of information
necessarily for Indian topics, but
whatever. Let's just look at this. So,
so this is this is what remained of the
Kesha Tupa about a century and a half
ago. Shajikadhera,
outskirts of of Peshawar and now
apparently there are slums on top of it.
So, how tall was this uh structure was
this building?
Uh meters, let's see, meters or feet or
whatever.
Okay. Height was about
120 m to 170 m which is pretty big. So
400 ft to 560 ft. That is how tall the
kaneshka was. It was built about roughly
18 or 1900 years before today. Huge
building. Huge. Huge. the tallest
building in the known world possibly at
the time. That's one of the high-rise
buildings from ancient times. But that
once again was a temple or a stupa. It
was a religious structure. It was not a
building where people lived during the
sarasati sindu phase of our history. We
had multi-story buildings in the
metropolitan areas like Kalibangan and
Raki and Harpa and Mahindo and so on. We
had multi-storied buildings but not
high-rise buildings.
So the kadeshupa was not a building that
was intended for human habitation. It
was never used for that.
When did we first have hire? You had
something called the Manhattan of the
desert in Yemen, right? What was the
Manhattan of the desert?
The desert.
Yemen. I forget the name of the
Sheibbam. Sheam.
Sheam in Yemen's Hadra region.
Shibbam. So if you look at Shebam, so
first of all,
how old is it? It was founded in the 3rd
century AD.
And uh
yeah, so if you look at this city,
ancient city, you will see high kind of
high-rise buildings, multi-story
buildings like 7 8 stories high. And
this was built several centuries ago.
So, does it tell us how when these tall
buildings were first constructed?
[snorts]
Um, not sure what it says.
So, it's been in existence for about
1700 years. Shibbam. So, that's an
example of uh high-rise buildings.
So, multi-story buildings were in
existence 5 6 thousand years ago in
India. the Sarasati Sindu phase of our
history. We had the Kaneshka stupa that
was built about 18 or 1900 years ago
which was a gigantic building. You had
the Shibam Shibbam city of Shibbam in
Yemen where you have possibly thousand-y
old multi-story buildings reasonably
high-rise buildings maybe 7 800 years
old that sort of thing. So eventually
this this happened obviously over time
gradually
and the proper first proper proper
high-rise buildings or skyscrapers
uh those were constructed in the United
States in the in the 19th century.
So you had Otus, the engineer who
invented the elevator, which is also
called a lift. And that made it possible
for for humans to build really tall
buildings and you could just go into the
elevator and go to whichever floor you
wanted. You didn't have to climb all the
way up. And so that was a transformative
invention, the elevator. And that's that
opened up architecture to creating
really tall structures, tall buildings.
And that was the rise of there was the
beginning of of the era of of of
skyscrapers in North America. So that's
where the proper skyscrapers really
high-rise buildings come into existence.
Uh but yeah, tall buildings have been
around for for centuries, maybe even
millennia,
right? Um what next? What question do we
have next?
Amisha says the current theory is that
the Indo-Uropean language was spread by
a step nomad culture. Yeah, that's the
Arian invasion, migration,
tourism picnic model, isn't it? That's
the current theory, the the the the
mainstream theory. So
apparently al as per this mainstream the
the currently accepted mainstream
consensus the Indo-Uropean language was
spread by a step nomadic culture. How
were there so many people living in the
steps during the Neolithic period right?
First of all what is the Neolithic
period? The Neolithic period is this a
new stone age roughly 10,000 years
roughly 10,000 BC to about 2,000 BC
roughly roughly okay you I'm sure other
other people will will have different
interpretations but you could say it's
10,000 BC to about 2,000 BC that is the
Neolithic period the new stone age and
it is said that this is the time where
our ancestors
shifted from being nomadic hunter
gatherers to becoming agriculturalists.
And because they became
agriculturalists, they had to settle
down. They had to start domesticating
animals. They had to set up permanent
settlements in villages and towns and
cities eventually. And they developed
new technologies like polished stone
tools and pottery and weaving eventually
metallergy. And this is the time when
you have the dawn of civilization that
is the Neolithic period. Okay. So the
theory is that um the Indo-Uropean
language was spread during this period
by step nomads. So what is the step? We
know what nomadic people are. People who
move from one place to another and they
never stay in one place for too long.
But what is the step? The step is the
Euro Eurasian step.
this vast region from uh you could say
the singing jang part of present day
China
it encompasses the entirety of central
Asia Kyrgystan Tajakistan Kazakhstan
mainly mainly Kazakhstan and it also
includes Eastern Europe which is uh
Ukraine southern Russia etc and it also
includes part of part parts of Siberia
and It also encompasses Mongolia
actually.
Okay. So that is the Eurasian step.
Huge region uh 8 to 10,000 kilometers
wide. That's the region we're talking
about.
Okay. So so that is the Eurasian step.
Now what were the populations like in
the known world outside of Africa? At
the time no one knew about I mean no one
from our perspective our ancestors
perspective nobody knew about Australia
or the Americas
uh what was the what were the
populations like in Eurasia at this
time. So the total population of the
world was maxim of of Eurasia during the
Neolithic until about uh 2000 BC was
about maximum 20 million.
So the Indian subcontinent would you you
may have had maybe 8 million people that
lived in the Indian subcontinent. When
it comes to
China you might have had another 8
million people who lived in China. So
that there you have 16 million right
right away. Then west of the Indian
subcontinent you have the Persian
plateau region maybe half a million
maybe 1 million people there. Then you
have Anatolia.
Okay maybe half a million people in
Anatolia. If you take the whole of
Europe maybe a couple of million people
maximum 5 million okay the Eurasian step
this gigantic vast region that we spoke
about just now maybe
half a million people maximum probably
200,000 people maybe 300,000 people
so the Eurasian step had people but the
population densities were incredibly low
at the time and you put all of these
population groups together India, China,
Eurasia, Anatolia, Persia,
um Europe, all of this together, you may
have maximum 20 million people, possibly
less than that. So the step region had a
tremendously low population density and
unlike India or China where you had
settled populations
and proper civilizations maybe 5,000
years ago unlike India and China or even
Persia in the step region you had hunter
gatherers you had nomads maybe early
agriculturalists.
So despite there being settled
populations and and civilized
populations in in India, in China, even
Persia, Anatoli, etc. in the step
regions, you still had nomadic hunter
gatherers who lived there. So the
populations weren't high. The population
over the step wasn't high at all. Half a
million maybe. Some people may say 1
million. But if you look at the actual
area it encompasses, the population
density density is still incredibly low.
So that was the situation.
And then how how how
does a nomadic step culture give rise to
a high civilization like India?
Makes no sense. The culture of a of a of
nomadic hunter gatherers. It gives gives
rise to the high civilization of India.
How does it make sense? It makes sense
apparently to some people.
Okay.
Okay. We still have a lot of more
questions I can take.
But I'm out of time. We have crossed two
hours. So maybe I will take some
questions from the live chat. Okay,
there are some super chats. Let me let
me take those. Um,
okay. What's the first of all, we have
Divali who is a new member. Welcome to
the membership. Thank you very much for
becom becoming a member. I really
appreciate that. Thank you.
WBR says did the US really send send its
aircraft carriers towards India in 1971
since there's no mention of it in
western literature and media
my recent my opinion recent statement
about Russia
by Russia ambassador to Bangladesh okay
we'll not discuss geob I'll discuss
history did the US really send aircraft
carriers it sent one aircraft carrier
strike group the US's enterprise there's
no mention of it in literature in media
Yeah. Really? How did you come to that
conclusion? Uh,
how did you come to that conclusion?
Okay. 9 1971
USS Enterprise
Bay of Bengal.
There's no mention really. It's all over
the place.
It's all over the place. all over media.
I'm sure there are books about this
books.
The fall of Dhaka, stories of great and
glory, I don't know,
books of
wars without war by black man and
Kaplan, the Indian end of the
celelescope by Ji Ranandani, the throne
and confrontation by Arl. So there's
plenty of books, there's plenty of
academic papers.
The Americans sent an aircraft carrier
strike group led by the USS Enterprise,
an aircraft carrier which had a bunch of
other destroyers around it and maybe
submarines as well. The British also
sent an aircraft carrier strike force
strike group into the Bay of Bengal. So
the there was one American strike group.
There was a British strike group. There
were two aircraft carrier strike forces,
strike groups sent to intimidate India.
It's a fact. Everyone knows it. So there
you have it.
Um, Brown Leprechaun says, "Could you
please discuss the Muslim Brotherhood
and its history?" Well, well, that's
something I haven't really gone into in
great depth.
It did it emerge out of Egypt? It did
entrench itself in Egypt. The Al Azar
University kind of in in Cairo is kind
of uh its ideological
um home ground possibly.
No, I'm not very clear about the exact
history of the Muslim Brotherhood. I
see I [laughter]
it's not something I I've studied in in
great detail. It's something it's
definitely something interesting and
maybe I should study this and and go
into the bottom of this but I at this
point in time I will not be able to give
you a proper history of the of the
Muslim Brotherhood.
Sorry about that. I can't know
everything. It's not possible for one
person to know everything. So I have not
really looked into into this into this
specific matter. It's definitely an
important aspect of history and the
present day world also but yeah not
right now. I can't. Sorry. Rush God is a
new member. Thank you very much for
becoming a member. Let us all welcome
Rush God to the membership of the
channel. Thank you very much indeed.
MXG lol haha says breast ripper was used
by Francis Xavier. These clamps were
heated to rip the breast of Hindu women
who refused to convert. Today these go
these Hindus go to the saint to the same
St. Francis Xavier church for
sightseeing and prayers. It's because
see it's true. It's true. Let let's
let's Google this since you're
mentioning it, right? A Goa Inquisition
breast ripper.
The breast ripper.
This hideous instrument.
I mean, imagine how evil the people are
who used such instruments on on helpless
people.
Right.
Breast ripper used by missionaries led
by Francis Xavier and Goa. These iron
clamps were heated to red hot
temperatures and used to rip the breasts
from Hindi Hindu women who opposed
conversion. If the woman didn't die, she
would be horribly disfigured.
I mean
that's the kind of barbarity we have
endured or our ancestors and our people
have endured. And today
our people go to these churches for
sightseeing and prayers. Look, I don't
blame the people. We don't teach this
history to our kids in school, in
college, university. None of this is is
taught.
We are taught a whitewashed sanitized
version of history in which the foreign
oppressors are our saviors.
That's the fault of the education system
that the government refuses
to reform.
Maybe some small changes have happened
recently but nothing significant,
nothing major. So yes, you are
absolutely entirely correct. This is
just one example of the brutality of the
barbarity that was unleashed on the
people of India by these monsters.
Yeah.
[laughter]
MXG Lha says, "I hoped you had a very
merry Christmas and you prayed at the
St. Francis Xavier Church. You see, this
year I was so unfortunate that I I
completely forgot there was this
festival called Christmas and I
completely forgot to pray at the phrase
St. Francis uh Xavier Church, which I
have never done before. Um maybe next
year I may consider doing some some kind
of excursion possibly." Yeah. So,
[laughter]
okay, got it. Thank you. Okay, that
brings me to the end, I suppose, of
today's live stream. All the super chats
are done.
And now we can discuss anything we want.
Apparently, hair care routine. What's my
[laughter] hair care routine? Okay,
editor, please don't take any of these
questions. These are not these
[laughter] don't matter.
[clears throat] What's my hair care?
Just wash your hair. Yeah, every other
day, maybe three times a week. That's
enough. No other hairare routine. Um,
[laughter]
okay.
Um,
see
what else do we have?
Aino says, "Everyone intuitively knows
Nazism is objectively evil. This
intuition already assumes objective
moral law. This is objective. But you
are saying objective on subjective
level." I'm not sure what you're saying,
sir. I'm not sure what you're saying.
You are too intelligent for me, sir. My
brain can't wrap around itself, wrap
itself around that. Um, okay. Anyway, so
I think we can now
uh
can we take more questions maybe for
some for some time perhaps? Aayush Singh
says was nonviolence in India's freedom
struggle a British encouraged diversion
to prevent an Americanstyle armed
revolution
Mr. Gandhi and Mr. Neu became faces of
those diversions. Question mark. Look
who founded the the the political party
that was um at the forefront of the
nonviolent resistance
who found the Indian National Congress.
Yeah. Who founded? Who founded? Who
founded the Indian National Congress?
The Indian National Congress was founded
by Alan Octavian Hume, a retired British
British civil servant. He is referred to
as the father of the Indian National
Congress.
Alan Octavian Hume,
the great hedge of India. Have you
thought, have you heard of the great
hedge of India?
Does it say anything about the hedge of
India over here?
uh the Indian inland customs line. This
guy Alan Octavin Hume,
he
implemented this inland customs line
that caused
the deaths of millions. You can look
into the details and he founded the
Indian National Congress which was at
the forefront of the nonviolent
resistance against the British. Imagine
if there was a political party that was
all about violent resistance, armed
resistance. It would have given rise to
an American style armed revolution.
So I think you can all come to your own
conclusions based on that. Yes.
Okay.
Be care group R2 originate was it mainly
why is it mainly found in India? I think
R itself originates in India. Downstream
of R you have R1 R2 then downstream of
that you have R1 A R1 B R2 or whatever
that sort of thing. So the parent hypo
group is R and the parent hog group of R
what is the parent hypo group of R
eventually you will come to HLO group F
which is upstream of R and F itself
originates in India.
So what does Wikipedia say about HLO
group R2? Let's see.
HLO group R2.
Uh yeah, it's found in so-called South
Asia. What does Wikipedia say about this
place of origin? Obviously
South Asia or Central Asia. And what is
upstream of Yeah, upstream of R2 is R.
What's the place of origin? North Asia
really. It's the Indian subcontinent.
An ancestor is P M something. Anc
ancestor is P.
Where is P once again? Indian
subcontinent. What's its ancestor?
K2B was it? Before that you have K2.
Before that you have K. What is before
K? I J K. Before I JK you have
uh HI J K
G HI J K and above that you have F.
and F as you can see where it
originates.
So look eventually the truth will come
out.
The ancestry is in India
right? Okay.
Um
so this is why I do I I prefer to take
live stream questions from the super
chat so that I don't have to think which
one to pick. There are so many going on
here. If I have super, I just pick the
super without
pick them all. That's it. Um
um what do we have? Why no videos on the
Bangladesh issue?
Do I have to?
Which Bangladesh issue? The Hindu Muslim
thing that's going on. Look man, look
people, I
can't make videos about everything.
I look into history, geopolitics,
science. The Bangladesh issue is not a
historical issue. It's not a scientific
issue. In geopolitics, it is an issue.
It's not a major issue.
So, let the various popular YouTubers
make those videos. I don't have to talk
about everything. You ask me questions
about this during a live stream. I will
certainly take up the question. I'm not
making a separate video about this.
Okay.
Okay. I suppose I can end the live
stream now. See these questions I've
answered so many times.
So many times I've answered these
questions. Of course I understand that
many of you are new viewers. So I
totally get it. So let me answer this
answer this question. Why did we have to
face millennia of humiliation? No, we
did not face multiple millennia of
humiliation. We faced one millennium of
humiliation.
The Chinese like to speak about their
century of humiliation when they were
oppressed by the west.
We in India were oppressed by first the
Turks and then by the Europeans total
for a thousand years. So that's a
millennium of humiliation. How did this
happen?
It happened because we eventually got
conquered by foreigners, barbarians.
How do you get conquered and why do you
get conquered? You get conquered by
foreigners if you are weak.
When you have a region as large as a
subcontinent,
you need political unity and stability.
If you have political unity and
stability, nobody can conquer you. So we
had periods of time when you had the
Morian Empire, the Shunga Empire, the
Kushan Empire, the Gupta Empire, the the
Chola Empire,
the Maratha Empire and so on.
Periods of time when the whole
subcontinent was essentially united
under a single political center.
During such periods of time, nobody can
even think of invading and defeating
you. But when you are fragmented,
what happens is that you have multiple
kingdoms who are all adversaries of each
other. That's when foreigners can come
and take advantage of that and conquer
you. And that's what happened. So we
were invaded by the Turks when we were
in a period of fragmentation and that's
why the situation went downhill from
there onwards. That's the reason why we
had to face a millennium of humiliation
which is still not over. By the way, we
are still colonized.
So,
okay.
Uh, what else do we have? Okay, I'll
I'll just take one more question. Um,
Ankita Kachab, good to see you, ma'am. A
question by Moonlight Sonata 123.
thoughts on the US Manta project. What's
a Manta project? I know about the
Manhattan project. What is the Manta
project? Let's Google it. I'm not sure.
I unfortunately will not know about
every project. What is the US Manta
project? Uh US Manta Project?
Manta Ray Project or Manta Project?
Manta Ray. Manta ray project
or is it a Manta project? The question
is US Manta project. What is that? US
Manta project is DARPA's Manta ray
uncrrewed
underwater vehicle. A large autonomous
long duration submersible designed for
deep sea missions capable of carrying
payloads like mines and torpedoes or
harvesting and harvesting energy from
the ocean
extra-large underwater
uncrrewed underwater vehicle
and so on. So this is the weaponization
of robotics of of AI. Yeah, that's what
it is. So this can do very nice things
but it also can do military activities.
So yeah that's what it is. We are now
entering an era where we're going to see
the synthesis of artificial intelligence
with robotics
and you're going to have autonomous
vehicles that can operate independent of
human control or with human control plus
AI inputs hybrid form and they can auto
potentially auto operate autonomously
for days or weeks on end without the
need for human intervention.
And such vehicles if if deployed in
swarms of thousands
can give you essentially hedgeim money
over the oceans. So yeah,
interesting that this is happening and
no surprise. So every nation that has an
industrial base and reasonable on on
amount of brains, they should invest in
these technologies now otherwise you're
going to be left behind.
Okay. UMX says video on more myths
Indian believe in when I'll see about
that. Is it is it a pressing issue right
now? I already have one video about the
major myths that Indians believe in.
Um I'll I'll see about that. I'll see
the major myths that I think I've
covered them. Right. We'll see. Maybe.
Okay. So, that brings me to the end of
today's live stream. Thank you very much
everybody. Almost two and a half hours.
Really appreciate the questions. Really
enjoy the questions. Thank you so much
everybody for asking questions and
tomorrow we're going to have another
live stream which is going to be an ask
me anything any topic whatsoever based
on the super chat that way I can just
don't have to look for questions I can
just pick all the questions that's it so
I look forward to seeing you there
tomorrow
um I'll take as many questions as
possible over the over maybe two three
hours and please ask me whatever it is
that you're interested in I look forward
to that I look forward to seeing you
there tomorrow until then take care keep
learning Keep asking questions. Keep
raising your standards. See you all
tomorrow, 8:00 p.m. India time. Until
then, take care. Bye-bye.